你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到pwn学院
welcome to pwn College
我是Yan，今天我们要讨论的是
I'm Yan and today we're going to talk about
汇编中的控制流
control flow in assembly
我们了解了寄存器
so we've learned about registers
了解了内存
we've learned about memory
了解了数据
we've learned about data
这很好
that's great but
现在我们可以编写一个程序来处理数据
we can now write a cool program to crunch a bunch of data
但它是如何判断
but how does it make decisions on whether or not
这个数据是好的
that data is good
这个数据处理好了，等等
that data has been crunched well etc etc
这些判断由能影响控制流的指令做出
we make these decisions using control flow impacting instructions
我们在这里讨论一下
which we'll talk about here
首先
first
我们看看CPU是如何执行数据的
let's look at how a CPU actually executes data
抱歉，执行代码的
of course sorry actually executes code
冯·诺伊曼架构中，汇编指令就是简单的数据
assembly instructions are in von Neuman architecture are simply just data
正如我们说过的
as we talked about
汇编会直接转换成二进制代码
assembly directly translates into binary code
程序加载时，被吐到内存中
which is then just like spewed into memory when your program is loaded
然后直接传递给CPU
and is then passed directly to the CPU
所以在内存的某个地方
so somewhere in memory
无论程序加载在哪里
wherever your program is loaded
本例中是0x40800
in this case at 0x40800
这里有一个pop rax
there's a pop rax
然后 pop rbx
and then a pop rbx
接着是 add rax, rbx
and then an add rax rbx
然后是push rax，存储计算结果
and then push rax for the result
这是人类可读的形式
and this is human readable form
实际上在40800处，它是二进制码
in reality it's the binary code at 40800
有一个0x58
there's a 0x58
表示pop rax
that's pop rax
这就是转换后的字节码
that's literally what the bytes translates to
然后是pop rbx
then there is a pop RBX
就是 5b
that's 5b
它在内存地址40801处
and that's at 40801 the memory address
然后下个指令有3字节
then there're 3 bytes
因为add RAX RBX需要3个字节来编码
because add RAX RBX takes 3 bytes to encode
X86是所谓的变长指令集架构
x86 is what is called a variable width instruction set architecture
事实上，大多数流行架构都是变长指令集
in fact most popular architectures are variable width
我以后会证明
I will back that statement up in a second
但是x86中，不同架构（口误）
but x86 depending on the architecture
编码出的字节数是不同的
there's a different amount of bytes that's going to encode
不同指令
depending on the instruction
编码出的字节数是不同的
there's a different amount of bytes that's going to encoded
有一些架构声称是定长的
there are some architectures that claim to be fixed width
ARM就是其中之一
ARM is one of them
这个架构超越了x86
the architecture that is outcompeting x86
但公平的说，并没有
but wouldn't do so in a fair and just world
ARM也有很多非标准长度的指令
but ARM has plenty of non standard length instructions
实际上，任何人对ARM的任何宣称，都只是宣称
realistically every claim that anyone makes about ARM is crap
ARM垃圾
ARM is crap
X86最棒
x86 is the best
我首创的说法
you heard it here first but the
总之，这个指令占3个字节
TLDR 3 bytes to this instruction
x86变长指令集带来的影响
and the impact of the fact that x86 is a variable width architecture
在以后的模块中会变得更加重要
that becomes much more important later on in future modules
就像蓝色的??材料
in like the blue ?? material
但是现在
but right now
就是这样
this is just how it is
add rax,rbx在40802, 03, 04处
so add rax, rbx instructions at 40802 3 and 4
然后40805处
and then at 40805
3个字节
3 bytes
40805处，1字节
40805 1 byte boom
这被直接吐入到内存
and this is just spewed into memory
然后CPU执行它
and then the CPU executes it
好的，CPU知道要执行它
all right and the CPU knows to execute it
因为rip指令指针指向这里
because rip the instruction pointer is just like pointed here
RIP里是的这个值
it has this value
所以CPU下次执行时
and so the next time the CPU runs
会执行这条指令
it'll execute this instruction
然后再将指针指向下一条指令
and then point the pointer to the next instruction
然后重复这个过程
and then repeat
那如果你想跳过一条指令呢
so what if you want to skip an instruction
你可以
well you can
你可以使用jmp
you can use jump
这个语法有点疯狂
now this is a bit of a crazy syntax
或者说跳转标签在汇编中有一点点复杂
let's say one complex syntax in assembly is jump labels
这里mov CX 1337
so this mov CX , 1337
我们在尝试写一个在开头看到的函数
and recall we're trying to make a little function that we saw in the beginning
它就检查个值
that just checks some value
看值是否设置，来将leetness设置为1337或0
and sets our leetness to 1337 or 0 depending on if that value is set
现在
now
我们把1337放到寄存器CX中
we move 1337 into a register CX
即，RCX的低16位
the lower 16 bits of RCX
然后跳转到这个标签
and then we jump to this label
跳转到STAY_LEET
say jump to STAY_LEET
这基本上是在说
and this basicly says hey
不要执行这个
don't execute this
我们跳过它
we jump over it
接下来我们要做的是push RCX
and then the next thing we do is push rcx
这就是它在内存中的布局
alright this is how it's laid out in memory
这是它汇编后的样子
and this is what it looks like when assembled
我是说，这不是实际内存中的布局
I mean this isn't how it's laid out in memory
这是语义上的，指令的布局
this is semantically how the instructions are laid out sequentially
这个跳转标签不是一条指令
this is because this jump label is not an instruction actually
它只是汇编这条指令时，汇编器的一个帮手
it's just a helper to assemble this instruction
这些是得到的字节
these are the bytes that result
这是mov cx 1337
this is mov CX 1337
你可以在这里看到小端序的1337
you can in fact see little endian 1337 right here
很酷啊
cool huh
66 b9是mov CX
and 66 b9 is mov CX
神奇
amazing mind blown
这是跳转，EB
this is jump EB
EB表示jmp
EB is jump
EB 04表示跳过4个字节，再执行
EB 04 means hey skip 4 bytes and then start executing
我们跳过这一条，mov cx, 0
boom we skip this guy which is mov sorry cx 0
抱歉，我也不知道为啥这里写的rcx
I don't know why I have RCX here
我的
my bad
然后直接执行push RCX
and then we directly execute push RCX
这个标签告诉我们这里填什么值
this label told us what value to put here
标签确实会被汇编
but the label does actually get assembled
但它就是一个供汇编器使用的标签
it's just a label for the assembler to use
现在
now
有趣的是这个跳转指令很酷
interesting thing is this jump instruction is kind of cool
它是一个有符号跳转
it is a signed jump
这是一个有符号的值
this is a signed byte variable so a value
如果是FF
so if it is FF
它会向后跳1
it would jump backwards by 1
如果是Fe
if it's Fe
它向后跳2，fe是补码
it jumps backwards by 2 in 2's complement
那么向后跳是什么意思呢
now what does it mean to jump backwards
如果这是jmp 0
well if this was jump 0
它会给rip加0
it would add 0 to the instruction pointer
这就是jmp的原理
that's what jump does
给rip加一个值
adds to the instruction pointer
rip指向的是下一条指令
the instruction pointer is pointing at the next instruction
这里是40806
in this case 40806 this guy
如果我们jmp 0
if we jump 0
它就向rip加上0
it adds 0 to it
就正常执行下一条指令
just executes the next instruction
事实上，我确信它能运行
I actually I'm sure it'll work
我猜会汇编成nop（no operation）
I guess it would be a no op
不确定
I don't know
可能会有一些性能影响
probably have some performance implications
不管怎样
anyways
如果我们jmp -1
if we jump negative 1
它会跳到下一条指令前1字节处
it'll jump 1 before the next instruction
就是当前指令内
which is halfway through this instruction
它会把04当指令执行
it will try to execute 04 as an instruction
这可能是指令，也可能不是
which may or may not be an instruction
估计情况会很糟
probably you're going to have a bad time
如果jmp -2 eb fe
if you jump negative 2 ebfe
记住它
memorize that
因为调试汇编代码时，有时它很有帮助
because it's sometimes helpful in debugging assembly code
Eb fe跳回到自己
ebfe jumps back to itself
再次执行它
executes it again
跳回来
jumps back
这是一个无限循环
and it's an infinite loop
Eb fe在x86中是无限循环
ebfe is an infinite loop in x86
你可以直接写它
you can write it directly
太棒了，好的
it's awesome all right cool
这就是跳转jmp
so that's jump
但它仍然没有做判断
but that's still not making decisions
它就是跳过
that's just skipping no matter what
这个将永远不会被执行，直接跳过了
this will never be executed just skipped
jmp实际上对在代码中嵌入数据很有帮助
jump is actually very useful for embedding data in your code
你可以在这里放任何东西
like you can actually put anything here
你可以放一堆数据
you can put a bunch of data
你可以放一张图片
you can put an image
你可以放一个cad GIF，都没问题
you can put a cad gif and it all work
它会跳过去，继续执行
and it'll just jump over and keep executing
很简洁，但对做判断没有帮助
really neat but not useful for making decisions
我们来做一些判断
so let's make some decisions
我们可以用条件跳转来实现
we can do that with a conditional jump
这里我们可以把值移到CX中
and here we can move some value into CX
然后执行条件跳转
then we can make a conditional jump
跳转到标签继续执行
to our jump label and keep executing
这个条件跳转表示如果不为0则跳转
this conditional jump says jump if not 0
有很多条件跳转指令
and there's a bunch of conditional jumps
有相等则跳转
there's  jump if equal
不相等则跳转
jump if not equal
大于则跳转
jump if greater than
小于则跳转
jump if less than
小于等于则跳转
jump if less than equal
很多
is a lot of stuff right
我们在讨论什么
but what are we talking about
什么是相等
what is equal
这个说了标签是什么
I mean this said what the label
标签不是（判断）
the label is not like
标签是我们跳转的距离
the label is just how far we jump
就是这个家伙
that's this guy
那什么是相等
what is equal
什么是相等，是最后看的
what is equal is the last thing we checked for Equality
x86上这点很有趣
and this is very interesting about x86
很多现代架构也是
and actually many modern architectures
首先执行检查
you first check things
然后根据检查结果采取行动
and then you take actions on the checked things
所以这还不完整
so this actually isn't complete
我们首先要做的是检查
what we need is to first check something
我们说说条件
now let's talk about conditions
条件有点复杂
conditions are kind of crazy
X86有一个叫rflags的特殊寄存器
x86 has a whole special register called rflags
你不能随意用mov更改rflags
and you can't just like move in and out rflags
这是一个特殊寄存器
it's just a special register
有其他指令能访问它的部分
there's other ways other instructions that can access parts of it and so forth
基本上，rflags保存了一堆表示条件标志的位
basically rflags holds a bunch of bits representing condition flags
它就有它们
it just has them
位1是某个标志
bit 1 is some flag
位2是另一个标志
bit 2 is another flag
算术运算
and any arithmetic operation
尤其是比较运算和测试运算
but especially comparison operations and test operations
即cmp和test指令
so cmp and test
他们会更新这些标志
they update all of those flags
这些标志都有特定的含义
and these flags have specific meaning at a very low level
常用到的条件标志
the main conditional flags that are actually checked
在所有x86支持的各种条件中
to implement all of the various conditions that x86 support
有进位标志，CF
is the carry flag
算是
kind of let's say
不是所有情况都是
this isn't accurate in all cases
但这是一个有用的近似
but it's a useful approximation
CF表示
the carry flag says hey
在上个操作中
in this last operation
上个64位操作中
this last 64 bit operation
或32位操作
or 32 bit operation
或8位，或者其他大小的
or 8 bit or whatever the size
是多出来的1比特
was the kind of extra bit one
表示进位
was the carry bit one
比如，8位值中，0xff加1
so if in 8 bits we added 0xFF plus one
结果是0x00
that is 0x00
但，CF里，是1
that there is a 1 bit and that is the carry flag
这也可能将OF（溢出标志）置1
that would also set the overflow flag
看计算结果是否有从负数回绕到正数
did the result wrap between negative and positive
比如 补码为FFFF的值，是负数
so FFFF is negative in 2's complement
加上1，它就变成正的了
you add 1 it wraps around to positive
等等
wait was that
我好奇2个方向回绕都会改变这个标志吗
I wonder if it's set on both directions
不太确定
I'm not positive about it
因为很少会直接与标志寄存器交互
because you rarely interact with these flags directly
实际上会和这些跳转交互
you actually interact with these more semantic type of jumps
而不是这些跳转依赖的标志
that are than taken on those flags
SF（符号标志）表示上次操作结果是否为负数
signed flag was the result of the last operation negative
最左边的位，符号位，是否为1
was the was its left most bit the sign bit set
ZF（零标志）表示上次操作结果是否为0
or the zero flag was the result zero
如果你想检验某项是否相等
so if you wanted to check if something is equal
这是上一条指令
for example here's the last thing
比较两个值是否相等
two values are equal you compare
它会做个减法
which does a subtraction
但不像sub rax, rbx会将rax-rbx赋值给rax
but instead of sub rax RBX would say rax equals rax minus RBX
cmp rax, rbx只做减法
cmp rax, rbx just does the subtraction
更新标志位
updates the flags
然后丢弃计算结果
and throws out the result
cmp rax, rbx，然后相等则跳转到STAY_LEET
cmp rax, rbx and then jump if equal to STAY_LEET
实际上它才会检查，然后跳转
this will actually check the value and will jump away
test很适合检查0
test is good for testing for 0
这个test rax,rax，它会和自己按位与
so this test rax,rax it ands it against itself
如果是0
if it's 0
如果结果是0，它就跳转(口误)
if the result is 0 it'll jump (口误)
如果结果不为0，它才跳转
if the result is not 0 it'll jump
这将比较rax与rbx，rax大于rbx就跳转
this compares rax against rbx and does a jump if above
这是指无符号比较
that means it's an unsigned comparison
最棒的是
and the awesome thing
比较指令相同，且会设置相同的标志
is the same comparison instruction sets the same flags
但解释这些标志的方式
but how you interpret those flags
会根据有无符号改变
will change from unsigned to a sign
会根据是ja还是jg而改变
from an above to a greater than
jg，表示有符号比较
jump if greater that's a signed comparison
这样0xFFFFFFF小于0，因为它是-1
so hex fffffff is less than 0 because that's negative one
而ja
in a jump above
0xFFFFFF是一个非常大的数字
hex ffffff is a very large number
是无符号的
unsigned
它大于0
it's greater than 0
大多数情况下，这里是唯一在意有无符号的地方
and this is more or less for the most part the only place where signedness actually matters
当然还有其他的情况
I mean there's other cases of course
但这是最常见的
but this is the biggest one
所以有无符号是通过合适的跳转指令检查的
signedness is checked by using the right jump
甚至不是合适的比较指令
not even the right comparison
有无符号的数据，对应着相应的跳转指令
but the right jump for the right data type whether it's signed or unsign
你能从这两者看到区别
and you can see that the difference between
jg，有符号
greater than which is signed
ja，无符号
and above which is unsign
ja跳转要求CF为0，并且ZF为0
above checks that the carry flag is 0 and the zero flag is 0
jg要求ZF为0
whereas greater checks if the zero flag is 0
并且SF等于OF
and the sign flag equals the overflow flag
我不知道为什么这意味着大于
I don't know why that translates to greater than
你可以在网上查到
I mean you can look it up on the internet
它会解释的
and it'll explain it for you
我就不解释了
I won't explain it for you
它能起作用真是太酷了
it's pretty cool that it works
这一切都是通过这种简单的方式实现的
and it's all made possible this simple way
先进行比较，然后重点在于跳转
where you compare and then it's just the jumps are what matters
这都归功于补码
that's made possible by 2's complement
酷
awesome okay
现在有了条件
now that we have conditions
还有条件跳转
and we have conditional jumps
我们就可以实现有用处的循环了
we can actually make loops that do stuff
这是一个循环，会计数到10
so this is a loop that will count to 10
它将RAX设置为0
it sets RAX to 0
然后rax加1
it increments it
将其与10进行比较
it compares it against 10
如果小于10，它会跳转回去
and if it's less than 10 it will jump back
如果小于10，无符号小于
if it's below 10 unsigned less than
它会跳转回循环头
it'll jump back to loop header
当它没有跳转回循环头时
when it doesn't jump back to loop header
就继续执行后面的指令
just keeps going forward to the next instruction
此时rax是10
and now RAX is 10
好吧
okay
使用循环和控制流
with looping and control flow
我们几乎拥有编写任何程序所需的一切
we have almost everything we need to write any program
这很令人兴奋
this is exciting
我们可以编写电子游戏
we could write video games
我们可以写很多很酷的东西
we could write a lot of cool stuff
我们所需的还有一个东西，函数
all we need is one more thing functions
现代代码会分割成多个函数
modern code is split into functions
你写一个函数
you write a function
再调用函数
you call the function
最终归结为call和ret两个指令
well that in the end boils down to call and ret two instructions
Call保存它所在地址，然后跳转到别处
call saves the place it's at and goes somewhere else
这样ret就能返回到函数调用处的地址
so that ret can return to that place where you called the function
在C程序中
so in a C program
这是一个函数调用
this is a function call
执行这个
boom goes here execute this
回来
comes back
这是我们的checker
and this is our checker
我们整节课都在实现它
that we've been implementing this whole lecture
然后又调用了一次
then it calls it again
又上到这了
boom goes up there
返回时，它知道返回地址
and it knows when it returns
因为它在call时，保存了下一条指令的地址
and it knows because it saved the address of the next instruction after this call
就是它会回到的这个地址
that it'll go back to the this
汇编中是这样的
in assembly this is what it looks like
首先将第一个参数初始化为0
we first initialize the first argument to 0
传给check_leet
to check_leet
这是我们的check_leet函数
here's our function check_leet
它检测authed，即第一个参数，是否是0
it tests if authed the first argument is 0
如果是的话
if it is
哦，有问题
oops that's buggy
我来修正一下
let me fix that
这应该是jnz，稍等
this should be non 0 one sec
好了，现在对了
all right now it's correct
所以
so
这是我们的函数check_leet
this is our function check_leet
这里表示，第一个参数是不是0
right here say hey is the first argument zero
如果不是的话
if it is not
那就返回1337
then we're gonna be leet
我们通过rax返回1337
we're gonna return in RAX 1337
否则
otherwise
它从这里
so it goes here
跳转
jumps
执行这个
it executes this
否则如果rdi
otherwise if rdi
我们用来传递第一个参数的寄存器
the register we're using to pass the first argument
是0
is 0
我们mov ax，0
we'll move ax
它（rax）是我们用来传递返回值的寄存器
which is what the register we're using ,rax, to pass the return value
我们将把ax初始化为0
we're going to initialize it to 0
然后返回
and then we're going to return
当返回时
all right when this return happens
这两个返回都一样
either of these returns
当这个调用发生时
when this call happens
我们把这个地址，下条指令的地址，压入栈
we push the address of this guy the next instruction
我们把rip的值压入栈
we put the value of rip onto the stack
再执行这个函数
we go to the function
函数返回时
when it returns
我们把这个值弹出栈
we pop that value off the stack
然后回去
and we go back
我们
and we can keep
我们回到下一条指令继续执行
we go back to the next instruction continue execution
我们用参数0调用了cheek_leet
so we call check_leet with argument 0
然后cheek_leet返回后，我们继续执行
then we continue going when check_leet returns
又用参数1调用了一次
we called it with argument 1
然后我们调用exit
and then we call exit and boom
下节课我们会讲到如何退出程序
and we'll talk about how to exit a program in the next video
太酷了
boom how cool is this
我们有了一个用汇编代码编写的程序
we have a program in assembly code
里面包含了函数等所有东西
where we have functions and everything
几节课就学完了它
and you just learned it over the course of a couple of lectures
希望这是一件让人震惊的事
hopefully that was a mind blown thing
现在你可能会问
now you might ask okay
但是在函数调用中
but function calls
变量名到处都是
you got variable names all over the place
我怎么设置变量名
how can I do variable names
汇编器中可能有一些宏，支持设置变量名
there's probably some macro support in the assembler to do variable names
比如，rax在这里叫bob还是别的什么
and say hey here rax is known as Bob or whatever
但是汇编很简单
but assembly so simple
它提供了变量名
it gives you the variable name
你有16个变量可以使用
you have 16 variables you can use
rax rbx rcx RDX RDI RSI RSP RBP
rax rbx RCX RDX RDI RSI RSP RBP
R8 r9 r10 r11 r12 r13 r14 r15
r8 r9 r10 r11 r12 r13 r14 r15
还有RIP可以读取当前地址
and RIP to read where you are
这太酷了
how cool is that
你不必担心变量的命名
you don't have to worry about naming variables
你需要担心它们用完
you do have to worry about running out of them
你得把它们放到栈上
you have to write them to the stack
然后在从栈上拿出来
and get them off the stack
但是你不用担心命名
but you don't have to worry about them
太好了
that's great
现在
now
寄存器有限
you have very few of these register guys
那如果
so what happens if
我们在这里设置了rdi
we set RDI here
然后我们还想在函数中用它
and we wanted to keep using it in this function
用RDI
set RDI
这将是一个坏消息
that would be a bad news
事实证明，函数遵守某一个约定
well it turns out that there's a contract that functions agree on
称为调用约定
call the calling convention
被调函数和调用函数约定了
callee and caller functions agree
哪些寄存器将用于amd64上的参数传递
which register going to be used for arguments on amd64
我们刚才说的是RDI
which what we were talking about it's RDI
它用于第一个参数
hey remember that's what we used for the first argument
第二个是RSI
that RSI for the second
第三个是RDX
RDX for the third
第四个是RCX
RCX for the fourth
还有R8 R9
R8 R9
然后返回值放在rax
and then the return value is going to go into rax
如果你注意了，我们也用过它
which hey if you're involved we also used
寄存器是共享的
registers are shared again
所以调用约定也需要
so the calling convention also needs to
定义谁负责保存数据
define who is responsible for saving data
基本上是这样的
and it basically like this
如果你调用了一个函数
if you call a function
该函数保证会还给你原来的
it promises to give you back
RBX RBP R12 R13 R14和R15
RBX RBP R12 R13 R14 and R15
和调用前的状态一样
back in the same state it found it
如果它要改变这些寄存器
so if it's going to make changes to those
它首先会保存他们
it'll first save them
通常保存在栈上
usually on the stack
它会把它们保存在栈上
on the stack it'll save them on the stack push them all
然后修改它们
then it'll modify them
根据需要使用它们
use them however it needs
在返回之前，它会把它们从栈上弹出
and before returning it'll pop them all off
其它寄存器都可以随便用
everything else is up for grabs
当然除了RSP
of course it's except RSP
用的都是同一个栈
you're all using the same stack for these temporary storages of things
所以它会被维护
so it's gonna be maintained
其它的寄存器都随便用
everything else is up for grabs
如果你不希望rcx被你调用的函数破坏
if you don't want RCX to be destroyed by a function you call
就把它保存到栈上
save it onto the stack
只需调用前压入栈，被调返回后，弹出栈
just push it and pop it after you call the function
这叫做调用方保存的寄存器
that's called Caller Saved Registers
这就是x86中的控制流
and that is how control flow works in x86
现在你可以写一个简单的程序了
and now you can actually write a simple program
除了一个烦人的问题
except for this nagging question
该如何退出
how do you quit
几张ppt前，我们调用了exit
we called this exit function a couple slides ago
我在那里标了问号
and I just have question marks
请收看下个视频，你会找到答案的
well tune in to the next video and you'll find out